<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Loïc N. Michel</title>
    <link>/categories/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="/categories/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Site content: Loïc Michel &amp;middot; Photographs: Loïc Michel, Phil Jane &amp; [Arnaud Abadie](https://seaescape.fr/)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/categories/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>DeepIso v1 is live!</title>
      <link>/post/deepisov1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/deepisov1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a great pleasure to finally introduce DeepIso (A global open database of stable isotope ratios and elemental contents for deep-sea ecosystems) to the public! 18677 fully documented measurements conveniently located a couple of clicks away, at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.17882/76595&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.17882/76595&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.17882/76595&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This collaborative database currently has data for 493 distinct taxa from multiple habitats (hydrothermal vents, cold seeps, cold water coral reefs, other benthic or pelagic environments). Almost global latitude (-62 to 67°) and longitude (-177 to 152°) coverage, and samples taken between 1989 and 2018 at depths up to 5209 m. It&#39;s been a tremendous amount of work to put that together, and would not have been possible without help from a cast of thousands. More info about the project and involved people &lt;a href=&#34;/deepiso/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope this database will be useful for the community. &lt;a href=&#34;/#contact/&#34;&gt;Get in touch&lt;/a&gt; if you have any questions or feedback, and especially if you want to contribute! Hopefully, this v1 is just the beginning. Help us grow DeepIso as much as possible by sharing data and/or advertising the database to any potentially interested colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/bush.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Example of targeted taxa: tubeworms Escarpia southwardae and mussels Bathymodiolus aff. boomerang from cold seeps. Picture: Ifremer, WACS cruise, 2011 (depth: 3160 m).&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/bush.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Example of targeted taxa: tubeworms &lt;em&gt;Escarpia southwardae&lt;/em&gt; and mussels &lt;em&gt;Bathymodiolus&lt;/em&gt; aff. &lt;em&gt;boomerang&lt;/em&gt; from cold seeps. Picture: Ifremer, WACS cruise, 2011 (depth: 3160 m).
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ARDECO successfully funded</title>
      <link>/post/ardeco/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/ardeco/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We just received the amazing news that our project ARDECO (Assessing Resilience of DEep COrals) was selected for funding by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://anr.fr/en/&#34;&gt;French National Research Agency (ANR)&lt;/a&gt;. For this 4-year (2021-2025) project, alongside colleagues from Sorbonne Université (FR), Océanopolis (FR), University of Aveiro (PO), and Memorial University of Newfoundland (CA), we&#39;ll be combining in situ sampling and observations with ex situ experiments in pressurized aquaria to understand how global change might impact multiple aspects of deep-sea coral biology. We will focus on the Bay of Biscay, where several coral species (&lt;em&gt;Desmophyllum pertusum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Madrepora oculata&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Solenosmilia variabilis&lt;/em&gt;) form reefs at depths between 650 and 2000 m. I&#39;ll be in charge of a work package about coral feeding and energy acquisition. Stay tuned for more info once the project starts&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/corals.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Deep-sea corals in the Bay of Biscay (pink, left: Desmophyllum pertusum, right: Madrepora oculata) and associated fauna (zoanthids, bryozoans and comatulids). Picture: Ifremer.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/corals.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Deep-sea corals in the Bay of Biscay (pink, left: &lt;em&gt;Desmophyllum pertusum&lt;/em&gt;, right: &lt;em&gt;Madrepora oculata&lt;/em&gt;) and associated fauna (zoanthids, bryozoans and comatulids). Picture: Ifremer.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
