<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Papers | Loïc N. Michel</title>
    <link>/tags/papers/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Papers</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Site content: Loïc Michel &amp;middot; Photographs: Loïc Michel, Phil Jane &amp; [Arnaud Abadie](https://seaescape.fr/)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Papers</title>
      <link>/tags/papers/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper on Antarctic amphipods</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-antarctic-amphipods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-antarctic-amphipods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New paper out in Antarctic Science! For this one, we looked at mouthpart morphology in several species of Southern Ocean amphipods. Specifically, we aimed to assess whether the tremendous ecological diversity found in Antarctic amphipods, that occupy many different ecological niches and hold an important place in food webs, was reflected in their mandible morphology, and if mouthpart specialization could be used to describe amphipod feeding habits. It turns out that while mandible morphology adequately depicted some aspects of amphipod trophic ecology (e.g. degree of dietary specialization, trophic position), links between mandible morphology and amphipod diet were seldom unambiguous or straightforward. Overall, mandible morphology on its own was generally not sufficient to precisely predict amphipod feeding strategies. However, when combined with other methods (e.g. gut contents, trophic markers), it constitutes a valuable source of information for integrative studies of amphipod ecological diversity in the Southern Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954102020000395&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954102020000395&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/mandible.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;The mandible of one of the studied species, Oradarea sp.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/mandible.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The mandible of one of the studied species, &lt;em&gt;Oradarea&lt;/em&gt; sp.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper about hydrothermal vent shrimps</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-hydrothermal-shrimps/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-hydrothermal-shrimps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After a few quiet months of cancelled conferences, postponed cruises, and home working, I&#39;m very happy to share some news about a new publication. This paper, just published in Royal Society Open Science, is the output of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Pierre_Methou&#34;&gt;Pierre Methou&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lsquo;s thesis at Ifremer, that focused on emblematic, symbiont-bearing, hydrothermal vent shrimps &lt;em&gt;Rimicaris&lt;/em&gt; spp. Here, we combined integrative taxonomy (morphological analyses, DNA sequencing) and ecological markers (stable isotopes of C, N and S) to re-examine ontogenic niche shifts and interspecific differences in resource use among &lt;em&gt;R. exoculata&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;R. chacei&lt;/em&gt;. It turns out that while both species transition from photosynthesis-based nutrition towards a chemosynthetic diet after settlement, there is consistent niche segregation between the two species throughout their life cycle. Those results provide a good illustration of the identification issues persisting in deep-sea ecosystems and the importance of integrative taxonomy in providing an accurate view of fundamental aspects of the biology and ecology of species inhabiting these environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more (for free) at &lt;a href=&#34;https://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsos.200837&#34;&gt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsos.200837&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/rimicaris.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;A juvenile of the hydrothermal vent shrimp Rimicaris chacei. Image: Pierre Methou, Ifremer.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/rimicaris.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A juvenile of the hydrothermal vent shrimp &lt;em&gt;Rimicaris chacei&lt;/em&gt;. Image: Pierre Methou, Ifremer.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper: impact of fluid preservation on sea stars stable isotope ratios</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-preservation-seastars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-preservation-seastars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New article out in Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry! This paper is the first output of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Baptiste_Le_Bourg&#34;&gt;Baptiste Le Bourg&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lsquo;s PhD thesis at ULiège. Baptiste&#39;s PhD focuses on Southern Ocean sea stars. For part of his work, we were keen to use sea stars sampled during past campaigns and archived in lab or museum collections. However, these samples are typically stored in fluid preservatives (formaldehyde and/ or ethanol), which can influence their stable isotope composition. Here, we performed a 2-year experiment on the temperate sea star &lt;em&gt;Marthasterias glacialis&lt;/em&gt;, and monitored how different modes of preservation would alter its stable isotope ratios of C, N, and S. Our results showed that the preservation method indeed affected stable isotope ratios, but that correction factors could be used to mitigate those biases. Therefore, under some conditions, fluid-preserved sea stars can be used for trophic ecology studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the article at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.8589&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.8589&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/marthasterias.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;The sea star Marthasterias glacialis. Image: Tato Grasso/Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA 3.0&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/marthasterias.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The sea star &lt;em&gt;Marthasterias glacialis&lt;/em&gt;. Image: &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Marthasterias_glacialis_Linosa_067.jpg&#34;&gt;Tato Grasso/Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper about carbon fluxes in Arctic fjords</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-arctic-fjords/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-arctic-fjords/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New article out in Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences! For this paper, lead by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iopan.gda.pl/ekologia/mwk/mwk.html&#34;&gt;Maria Włodarska-Kowalczuk
&lt;/a&gt;, we compared regional and local drivers of organic carbon fluxes in six fjords ranging from the North Atlantic (60°N) to the Arctic (81°N). Our results suggest that organic carbon content, origin and burial rates varied greatly according to latitude and presence of glacier inflow. This variability is important to take into account when trying to produce global estimates of fjord role in blue carbon storage, and for building scenarios of future climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the article at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2019JG005140&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2019JG005140&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/fjord.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Image: IOPAN, DWARF project&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/fjord.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Image: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iopan.gda.pl/projects/Dwarf/&#34;&gt;IOPAN, DWARF project&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Journal of Animal Ecology</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-journal-of-animal-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-journal-of-animal-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New paper about Antarctic seabirds, lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://ninadehnhard.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Nina Dehnhard&lt;/a&gt;, just out in Journal of Animal Ecology. We combined GPS logging and stable isotopes to understand how Antarctica’s tremendous seasonal variability affected habitat and food segregation among closely related and sympatrically breeding species. Results suggest that all three species have a generalist behaviour and exhibit considerable isotopic niche overlap. This might be explained by the optimal foraging theory: in a very productive but highly variable such as coastal Antarctica, being a generalist, although it increases risks of interspecific competition, might be essential to efficiently exploit mobile prey stocks.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2656.13078&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2656.13078&lt;/a&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/graphicalabstractlow.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Graphical abstract of the paper&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/graphicalabstractlow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Graphical abstract of the paper
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
