<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>News | Loïc N. Michel</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>News</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Site content: Loïc Michel &amp;middot; Photographs: Loïc Michel, Phil Jane &amp; [Arnaud Abadie](https://seaescape.fr/)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New website</title>
      <link>/post/new-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-website/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I thought that it was past time to dust off my old wordpress website. I&#39;ve decided to transition to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;-hosted &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;hugo&lt;/a&gt; site, and built this one using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/&#34;&gt;Academic theme&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://georgecushen.com/&#34;&gt;George Cushen&lt;/a&gt;, which I cannot recommend warmly enough. It took me a while to adapt, but luckily there are many high-quality learning resources out there, making the process rather painless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new website is still under construction, and it might therefore look a bit rough around some edges, or contain a few dead links. I&#39;m sorry about the inconvenience. Feel free to &lt;a href=&#34;/#contact/&#34;&gt;drop me a line&lt;/a&gt; if you notice anything weird.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/academic.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/academic.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper: impact of fluid preservation on sea stars stable isotope ratios</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-preservation-seastars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-preservation-seastars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New article out in Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry! This paper is the first output of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Baptiste_Le_Bourg&#34;&gt;Baptiste Le Bourg&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lsquo;s PhD thesis at ULiège. Baptiste&#39;s PhD focuses on Southern Ocean sea stars. For part of his work, we were keen to use sea stars sampled during past campaigns and archived in lab or museum collections. However, these samples are typically stored in fluid preservatives (formaldehyde and/ or ethanol), which can influence their stable isotope composition. Here, we performed a 2-year experiment on the temperate sea star &lt;em&gt;Marthasterias glacialis&lt;/em&gt;, and monitored how different modes of preservation would alter its stable isotope ratios of C, N, and S. Our results showed that the preservation method indeed affected stable isotope ratios, but that correction factors could be used to mitigate those biases. Therefore, under some conditions, fluid-preserved sea stars can be used for trophic ecology studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the article at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.8589&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.8589&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/marthasterias.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;The sea star Marthasterias glacialis. Image: Tato Grasso/Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA 3.0&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/marthasterias.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The sea star &lt;em&gt;Marthasterias glacialis&lt;/em&gt;. Image: &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Marthasterias_glacialis_Linosa_067.jpg&#34;&gt;Tato Grasso/Wikimedia Commons, CC-BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper about carbon fluxes in Arctic fjords</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-arctic-fjords/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-arctic-fjords/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New article out in Journal of Geophysical Research: Biogeosciences! For this paper, lead by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iopan.gda.pl/ekologia/mwk/mwk.html&#34;&gt;Maria Włodarska-Kowalczuk
&lt;/a&gt;, we compared regional and local drivers of organic carbon fluxes in six fjords ranging from the North Atlantic (60°N) to the Arctic (81°N). Our results suggest that organic carbon content, origin and burial rates varied greatly according to latitude and presence of glacier inflow. This variability is important to take into account when trying to produce global estimates of fjord role in blue carbon storage, and for building scenarios of future climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the article at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2019JG005140&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1029/2019JG005140&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/fjord.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Image: IOPAN, DWARF project&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/fjord.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Image: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iopan.gda.pl/projects/Dwarf/&#34;&gt;IOPAN, DWARF project&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Article about our research in FNRS.news</title>
      <link>/post/article-fnrs-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/article-fnrs-news/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our research about the influence of sea ice cover changes on benthic food webs in East Antarctica (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-44605-5&#34;&gt;this paper, specifically&lt;/a&gt;) has been featured in the last issue of FNRS.news, the Belgian Funds for Scientific Research (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frs-fnrs.be/en/&#34;&gt;F.R.S-FNRS&lt;/a&gt;)&amp;lsquo;s quarterly magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the article below, or look at the whole issue at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frs-fnrs.be/docs/Lettre/lettre117.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.frs-fnrs.be/docs/Lettre/lettre117.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/FNRSnews117.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/FNRSnews117.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Journal of Animal Ecology</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-journal-of-animal-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-journal-of-animal-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New paper about Antarctic seabirds, lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://ninadehnhard.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Nina Dehnhard&lt;/a&gt;, just out in Journal of Animal Ecology. We combined GPS logging and stable isotopes to understand how Antarctica’s tremendous seasonal variability affected habitat and food segregation among closely related and sympatrically breeding species. Results suggest that all three species have a generalist behaviour and exhibit considerable isotopic niche overlap. This might be explained by the optimal foraging theory: in a very productive but highly variable such as coastal Antarctica, being a generalist, although it increases risks of interspecific competition, might be essential to efficiently exploit mobile prey stocks.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2656.13078&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2656.13078&lt;/a&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/graphicalabstractlow.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Graphical abstract of the paper&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/graphicalabstractlow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Graphical abstract of the paper
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper: a new species of hydrothermal nematod</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-a-new-species-of-hydrothermal-nematod/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 13:35:22 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-a-new-species-of-hydrothermal-nematod/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New paper in BMC biology, lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Daniela_Zeppilli&#34;&gt;Daniela Zeppilli&lt;/a&gt;. This article describes a new species of nematod living in deep-sea hydrothermal vents of the Mid-Atlantic Ridge. Rather large for a nematod (up to 9 mm length), &lt;em&gt;Oncholaimus dyvae&lt;/em&gt; likely feeds on chimiosynthetic micro-organisms, and might host bacterial symbionts. Read more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/s40850-019-0044-y&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/s40850-019-0044-y&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/s40850-019-0044-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_742&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1418&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/09/oncholaymusdyvae.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;oncholaymusdyvae&#34;&gt; &lt;em&gt;Oncholaimus dyvae&lt;/em&gt; sp. nov. : head and buccal cavity (scale bar: 20µm).[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out in Chemosphere</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-out-in-chemosphere/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 13:41:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-out-in-chemosphere/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper entitled &amp;ldquo;Stable isotope ratios of carbon, nitrogen and sulphur and mercury concentrations as descriptors of trophic ecology and contamination sources of Mediterranean whales&amp;rdquo; just came out in Chemosphere. Co-lead by ULiège&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Marianna_Pinzone&#34;&gt;Marianna Pinzone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/France_Damseaux&#34;&gt;France Damseaux&lt;/a&gt;, this article shows that differences in dietary habits influence mercury contamination in Mediterranean cetaceans (sperm whales, fin whales and long-finned pilot whales). Read the paper at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.124448&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.124448&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.124448&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_751&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1210&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/whales_niches.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;whales_niches&#34;&gt; Isotopic and contamination niches of the studied species.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chubacarc cruise - 06/05-07/06/19</title>
      <link>/post/chubacarc-cruise-06-05-07-06-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2019 14:21:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/chubacarc-cruise-06-05-07-06-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From 06/05 to 07/06, I took part in the second leg of the Chubacarc research cruise. Onboard RV L&#39;Atalante, we spent 4 (intense) weeks sampling fauna in deep-sea hydrothermal vents from back-arc basins in the Pacific Ocean. The campaign was a success, as we not only come home with hundreds of samples, but also discovered a new vent field (stay tuned for more info about that soon-ish). I learned a lot of new things, as it was my first deep-sea cruise, and my first time sampling with a ROV. I could not have hoped for a better first experience,  and I&#39;m grateful to fellow scientists, but also to the ROV staff and ship crew for their crucial part in the mission&#39;s smooth operations. Check out the Chubacarc cruise blog: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/chubacarc/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/chubacarc/&#34;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/chubacarc/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (French only, sorry).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[gallery columns=&amp;quot;2&amp;rdquo; type=&amp;quot;square&amp;rdquo; ids=&amp;quot;767,764,765,766&amp;rdquo;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper: sea ice and food web structure in East Antarctica</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-sea-ice-and-food-web-structure-in-east-antarctica/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 13:17:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-sea-ice-and-food-web-structure-in-east-antarctica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long time in the making, I&#39;m very pleased to announce that our paper about how changes of sea ice cover impacts food web structure just came out in Scientific Reports. While many polar regions currently lose sea ice quickly, some parts of East Antarctica recently saw a lot of it, even in summer. Here, we used stable isotopes of C, N and S to build models which show that absence of summer sea ice breakup deeply influences dominant consumers&amp;rsquo; feeding habits. These results suggest that future changes of sea ice cover in Antarctica have the potential to cause drastic changes in food web structure, and therefore to impact benthic communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research was made possible through funding by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.belspo.be/&#34;&gt;Belgian Science Policy Office (BELSPO)&lt;/a&gt;, in the framework of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.belspo.be/belspo/brain-be/projects/vERSO_en.pdf&#34;&gt;vERSO&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.naturalsciences.be/en/science/do/98/scientific-research/research-projects/project/6210&#34;&gt;RECTO&lt;/a&gt; projects. It was also supported by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.institut-polaire.fr/language/en/&#34;&gt;French Polar Institute&lt;/a&gt; (IPEV), through the REVOLTA program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is freely available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-44605-5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-44605-5&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-44605-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Those enjoying a lighter read can have a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciences.uliege.be/cms/c_5170884/en/sea-ice-cover-increase-is-changing-the-invertebrates-feeding-habits&#34;&gt;ULiège&#39;s news release&lt;/a&gt; about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_739&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1502&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/michel_graphicalabstract.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Michel_GraphicalAbstract&#34;&gt; A graphical summary of observed changes in food web structure[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Science of the Total Environment</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-science-of-the-total-environment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2019 11:43:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-science-of-the-total-environment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New paper out! For this one, we (lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Ana_Pizzochero&#34;&gt;Ana Carolina Pizzochero&lt;/a&gt;) investigated how biological parameters and ecological habits influenced contamination by legacy and emerging organic pollutants (including chlorinated and brominated flame retardants, dioxins, and furans) in whitemouth croakers (a.k.a. corvinas, &lt;em&gt;Micropogonas furnieri&lt;/em&gt;) from Rio de Janeiro State, Brazil. This species is one of the most commercially important species along the Atlantic coast of South America, making its contamination a matter of public health. For more info, read the full paper at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.05.213&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.05.213&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.05.213&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_716&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;600&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/09/pizzo.jpg?w=2048&#34; alt=&#34;pizzo&#34;&gt; Correlation matrix between pollutant concentrations and biological parameters or ecological tracers[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2019 09:47:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our new paper entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Modelling species response to climate change in sub-Antarctic islands: echinoids as a case study for the Kerguelen Plateau&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; is out in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://heardisland.antarctica.gov.au/research/kerguelen-plateau-symposium/the-kerguelen-plateau-marine-ecosystems-and-fisheries&#34;&gt;Proceedings of the 2nd symposium on the Kerguelen Plateau: Marine Ecosystems and Fisheries&lt;/a&gt;. It is lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://thomassaucede.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Thomas Saucède&lt;/a&gt;, who leads the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.proteker.net/?lang=en&#34;&gt;PROTEKER&lt;/a&gt; research programme. This collaborative project, funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.institut-polaire.fr/language/en/&#34;&gt;French Polar Institute&lt;/a&gt; (IPEV) aims to assess impacts of global change on marine ecosystems of the Kerguelen Archipelago (Sub-Antarctic islands). Here, using sea urchins with contrasted ecological habits as model species, we explored ways to couple species distribution and isotopic niche models to gain a global view of species&amp;rsquo; realised niches, encompassing abiotic requirements as well as feeding preferences and ecological interactions. We believe this joint use holds great potential to help predict how species could adapt to future climate change. You can &lt;a href=&#34;http://heardisland.antarctica.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0007/229138/16-Saucede-FullMS.pdf&#34;&gt;read the paper here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_707&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1024&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/09/kerguelenurchins.jpg?w=2048&#34; alt=&#34;R Graphics Output&#34;&gt; Isotopic niches of the 3 studied sea urchin species[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Limnology &amp; Oceanography</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-limnology-oceanography/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 15:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-limnology-oceanography/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Is the trophic diversity of marine benthic consumers decoupled from taxonomic and functional trait diversity? Isotopic niches of Arctic communities&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; just came out in Limnology and Oceanography. In this paper, lead by IOPAN&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iopan.gda.pl/ekologia/mwk/mwk.html&#34;&gt;Maria Włodarska‐Kowalczuk&lt;/a&gt;, we looked at how environmental perturbations (here, glacier melting) influenced benthic diversity in Arctic fjords. Our results suggest that glacially impacted areas have a lower specific and functional diversity, but that impoverished communities living there occupy a similar isotopic niche and have comparable trophic diversity. We discuss of what could cause this situation, and how it is important for community resilience to environmental change. Check it out at &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.1002/lno.11174&#34;&gt;doi.org/10.1002/lno.11174&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_657&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;676&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/acanthostepheia_malmgreni.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/acanthostepheia_malmgreni.jpg?w=676&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; One of the many studied species, the amphipod &lt;em&gt;Acanthostepheia malmgreni&lt;/em&gt; (Photo © IOPAN)[/caption] [caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_658&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;676&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/hornsund.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/hornsund.jpg?w=676&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The study zone: Hornsund fjord, Svalbard Archipelago (Photo © IOPAN)[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funded project: unravelling energy pathways in hydrothermal vents through isotopic labelling</title>
      <link>/post/funded-project-unravelling-energy-pathways-in-hydrothermal-vents-through-isotopic-labelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 12:42:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/funded-project-unravelling-energy-pathways-in-hydrothermal-vents-through-isotopic-labelling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We just received news that our project entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Transfer of energy in hydrothermal vents - an &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; experiment&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; will be funded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.isblue.fr/&#34;&gt;ISblue (Interdisciplinary graduate school for the Blue Planet)&lt;/a&gt;. Together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Teresa_Amaro&#34;&gt;Teresa Amaro&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Gauthier_Schaal&#34;&gt;Gauthier Schaal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Marjolaine_Matabos&#34;&gt;Marjolaine Matabos&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jozee_Sarrazin&#34;&gt;Jozée Sarrazin&lt;/a&gt;, we will set up an deliberate isotopic tracer addition (pulse-chase) experiment in mussel beds from hydrothermal vents of the Mid-Atlantic ridge). In doing so, we aim to understand how symbiont-bearing Bathymodiolin mussels, that are considered foundation species, influence rates and pathways of carbon fixation in hydrothermal vent food webs . The experiment will likely be as challenging to set up as it is exciting. Stay tuned for more information!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_646&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;676&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/crabes-lucky-strike.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/crabes-lucky-strike.jpg?w=676&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Bathymodiolus azoricus bed and associated fauna (Lucky Strike hydrothermal field, Mid-Atlantic ridge). Picture © Ifremer.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BASIS Symposium 2019</title>
      <link>/post/basis-symposium-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2019 07:55:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/basis-symposium-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On 28 and 29/03, I participated in the 2019 edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.basis-online.eu/en/&#34;&gt;Benelux Association of Stable Isotope Scientists (BASIS)&lt;/a&gt; annual symposium. The event was impeccably hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nioz.nl/en/about/organisation/staff/marcel-van-der-meer&#34;&gt;our colleagues&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nioz.nl/en&#34;&gt;Royal Netherlands Institute for Sea Research (NIOZ)&lt;/a&gt; on the lovely island of Texel. Both days were packed with great talks and posters, fruitful discussions with both familiar faces and new acquaintances, and even a tour of NIOZ&amp;rsquo; (very impressive) stable isotope lab. As always with BASIS, a very productive and pleasant experience. Already looking forward for the 2020 edition in Brussels!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_641&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;676&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/basis2019.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/basis2019.jpg?w=676&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; A bird&#39;s eye view of the conference venue[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Freshwater Biology</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-freshwater-biology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 13:14:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-freshwater-biology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2019 starts well, as our new paper was just published in Freshwater Biology. It&#39;s quite a change of scenery from my usual research, as it focuses on anthropogenic impacts on freshwater ecosystems. We looked at how river channelisation influenced feeding habits of young-of-the-year fishes in River Meuse. Our results suggest that habitat modification could be linked with increased competition for food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/fwb.13239&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/fwb.13239&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/fwb.13239&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_613&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1238&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/latli-e1548255196508.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;latli&#34;&gt; Isotopic niches of young-of-the-year fishes in the two localities.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArDB competition winner</title>
      <link>/post/ardb-competition-winner/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 10:54:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/ardb-competition-winner/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elementar.de/en.html&#34;&gt;Elementar&lt;/a&gt; celebrated the launch of its new software, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.analyticalresultsdb.com/&#34;&gt;ArDB (Analytical Results Database)&lt;/a&gt;, with a competition to win a two-year licence. The challenge was to explain how one plans to use such a tool to develop new research in under a 100 words. I entered and was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.analyticalresultsdb.com/news/win-elementar-ardb-cloud-licence-and-smartwatch-winners-announced&#34;&gt;selected among the winners&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;m very thankful and thrilled to use this software to help developing our &lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.wordpress.com/deepseabase/&#34;&gt;upcoming open database&lt;/a&gt; of stable isotope ratios in deep-sea organisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/12/ardb.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/12/ardb.jpg?w=600&#34; alt=&#34;ardb&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lipids in the Ocean 2018</title>
      <link>/post/lipids-in-the-ocean-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 13:25:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/lipids-in-the-ocean-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From 17 to 22/11/2018, the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://marinelipids.sciencesconf.org/&#34;&gt;Lipids in the ocean: Structure, function, ecological role and applications&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; conference took place in Brest. It was a pretty intensive week, starting   with workshops about sample preservation and storage; best practices to analyse lipid data; and how to couple lipid markers with stable isotopes (co-hosted by yours truly). After that, we had three days of very diverse talks. While exhausting, the conference was very rewarding. I&#39;ve learned a lot and I am now full of new ideas to use lipid-based markers in the context of my research&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_622&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;700&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/11/lipids_in_the_ocean_grpsmall.png&#34; alt=&#34;lipids_in_the_ocean_grpsmall&#34;&gt; Participants of the &amp;ldquo;Lipids in the Ocean&amp;rdquo; conference[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CONNECT 3 - Roscoff, November 2018</title>
      <link>/post/connect-3-roscoff-11-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 13:23:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/connect-3-roscoff-11-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From 14 to 16/11/2018, I participated at the 3rd French colloquium on biology and ecology of chemosynthesis-based ecosystems (CONNECT 3), hosted by the Roscoff biological station. It&#39;s been a great opportunity to meet the national community of hydrothermal vents and cold seeps researchers, and to present our lab&#39;s latest results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_619&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1024&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/11/2018-11-15-16.14.29.jpg?w=2048&#34; alt=&#34;2018-11-15 16.14.29&#34;&gt; Roscoff on a sunny winter day[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-journal-of-experimental-marine-biology-and-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 13:41:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-journal-of-experimental-marine-biology-and-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our new paper is out in Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology. We used stable isotopes to show that Baltic seagrass meadows offer a stable environment to macrofauna, dampening seasonal changes in the food web when compared with bare sediments. It is another product of the fruitful collaboration between &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iopan.gda.pl/&#34;&gt;IOPAN&lt;/a&gt; (Gdansk, Poland) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uliege.be/cms/c_8699436/en/portail-uliege&#34;&gt;ULiège&lt;/a&gt; (Liège, Belgium).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the full story here:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jembe.2018.10.004&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jembe.2018.10.004&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jembe.2018.10.004&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_608&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;807&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/1-s2.0-s0022098118302211-gr3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;emiliaseason&#34;&gt; Conceptual model synthesising trophic links in summer and winter, in both unvegetated sediments and seagrass meadows.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back from IsoEcol 2018 in Viña del Mar, Chile</title>
      <link>/post/back-from-isoecol-2018-in-vina-del-mar-chile/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 13:23:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/back-from-isoecol-2018-in-vina-del-mar-chile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m just back from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://isoecol.com/2018/&#34;&gt;IsoEcol 2018 conference&lt;/a&gt; in Viña del Mar. As always with IsoEcol, it&#39;s been a fantastic occasion to interact with leading experts in isotope ecology in a friendly and laid-back way, and to present our newest results to the isotope community. It was my third IsoEcol, and it&#39;s been good to catch up with old friends and colleagues, and to make a few new ones. It&#39;s been an inspiring week, choke-full of amazing talks and posters. It has also been an opportunity to discover beautiful (yet chilly) Chile. Thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://harrodlab.net/&#34;&gt;Harrod lab&lt;/a&gt; and other organisers for a brilliant conference! Next IsoEcol will be in Vienna in 2020. I&#39;m already looking forward!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_626&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;4608&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/20180803_134850.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;20180803_134850&#34;&gt; ULiège&#39;s (and friends) delegation at IsoEcol 2018[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-estuarine-coastal-and-shelf-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 13:17:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-estuarine-coastal-and-shelf-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our new paper is out in Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science. We combined stable isotopes and gut contents to investigate how much macrofauna living in Neptune grass detritus accumulations actually feeds on dead seagrass fragments. Our results indicate that detritus is an important food source for primary consumers, and that detrital carbon is transferred to higher trophic levels through predation. These results complement those obtained by Mascart et al for meiofauna living in the same environment. Read more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2018.07.001&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2018.07.001&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2018.07.001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_605&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1280&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/07/remy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;remy&#34;&gt; Bidimensional ordination of investigated macrofauna, based on similarity of gut content composition.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Food Webs</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-food-webs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 14:35:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-food-webs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our newest paper just came out in food webs. We used stable isotopes and fatty acid trophic markers to show that, despite the &amp;ldquo;black box&amp;rdquo; approach often applied to meiofaunal consumers, there is actually considerable interspecific differences in the feeding habits of copepods living in Mediterranean seagrass detritus. Moreover, our results show that some copepods could (quite unexpectedly) rely on seagrass detritus for their nutrition. Read more at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fooweb.2018.e00086&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fooweb.2018.e00086&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fooweb.2018.e00086&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the last paper from Thibaud Mascart&#39;s PhD thesis, and it comes out quite timely as Thibaud now transitions into a less academic career. All the best to him for this new challenge!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_506&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1531&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.wordpress.com/2018/05/17/new-paper-in-food-webs/fig-5-assimilation-c-seagrass/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/06/fig-5-assimilation-c-seagrass.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Possible mechanisms that could explain how seagrass detritus could enter copepod diet and, through them, be transferred to higher trophic levels.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BASIS Symposium in Liège</title>
      <link>/post/basis-symposium-in-liege/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 14:42:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/basis-symposium-in-liege/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On 19 and 20/04/2018, University of Liège hosted the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.basis-online.eu/en/en-basis-symposium-2018/&#34;&gt;2018 symposium&lt;/a&gt; edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.basis-online.eu/en/&#34;&gt;Benelux Association of Stable Isotope Scientists (BASIS)&lt;/a&gt;. Gilles Lepoint and I acted as local conveners. Although it has been two exhausting days, we are very happy with how things went. Turnout was very good for the conference (over 100 attendees), the atmosphere was friendly and the scientific level of the presentations was excellent. The symposium provided many opportunities for interactions between stable isotope users and people actually involved in instrumentation development. Thanks to the priceless help of reliable volunteers and of the BASIS board members, everything ran smoothly and pleasantly. We are already looking forward for the 2019 symposium!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/06/dbi1dzrxkaarz1r.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/06/dbi1dzrxkaarz1r.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Ecological Indicators</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-ecological-indicators/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 13:15:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-ecological-indicators/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new paper in collaboration with our Polish colleagues, entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolind.2018.02.054&#34;&gt;Modification of benthic food web structure by recovering seagrass meadows, as revealed by trophic markers and mixing models&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; just came out in Ecological Indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this one, we combined stable isotopes and fatty acid trophic markers in a quantitative mixing model, to evaluate how presence of seagrass meadows influences food webs in the coastal Baltic Sea. You can read the paper here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/221262&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/221262&#34;&gt;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/221262&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_367&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;1280&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/jankowska-et-al.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/jankowska-et-al.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jankowska et al&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Conceptual model of trophic connections in vegetated (green arrows) and unvegetated (orange arrows) habitats in summer in the Puck Bay (Baltic Sea) based on mixing model results[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Functional Ecology</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-functional-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2018 13:17:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-functional-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.13076&#34;&gt;Similar levels of trophic and functional diversity within damselfish assemblages across Indo‐Pacific coral reefs&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Laura_Gajdzik&#34;&gt;Laura Gajdzik&lt;/a&gt;, just came out in Functional Ecology. Using stable isotopes and functional diversity indices, we showed that patterns of ecological diversity are consistent in distinct damselfish assemblages found in very different Indo-Pacific coral reefs. Very happy to see this one out after a long, demanding and bumpy reviewing process&amp;hellip; Congratulations, Laura!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our research in the spotlight</title>
      <link>/post/our-research-in-the-spotlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 09:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/our-research-in-the-spotlight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elementar.de/en/products/stable-isotope-analysis.html&#34;&gt;Elementar&lt;/a&gt;, our IRMS instrumentation partner, has devoted an instalment of their &amp;ldquo;Customer Spotlight&amp;rdquo; to our (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Gilles_Lepoint&#34;&gt;Gilles Lepoint&lt;/a&gt; and I) work at University of Liège&#39;s stable isotope facility. We&#39;re thrilled and humbled to stand there among big names in isotope analysis and biogeochemistry! You can &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elementar.de/en/news-events/detail/article/customer-spotlight-laboratory-of-oceanology-university-of-liege.html&#34;&gt;read the article here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_20170830_115134.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_20170830_115134.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20170830_115134&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First day at my new position</title>
      <link>/post/first-day-at-my-new-position/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 19:54:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/first-day-at-my-new-position/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was my first day as a research scientist at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wwz.ifremer.fr/deep_eng/&#34;&gt;Deep Environment Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; of Ifremer Brittany, Brest, France. I will miss my colleagues from &lt;a href=&#34;http://labos.ulg.ac.be/oceanologie/&#34;&gt;University of Liège&lt;/a&gt; (although I strongly hope to carry on working with them), but I&#39;m looking forward to new challenges and research opportunities as I now move into deep-sea research&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-in-canadian-journal-of-fisheries-and-aquatic-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 12:35:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-in-canadian-journal-of-fisheries-and-aquatic-sciences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New paper in collaboration with our Brazilian colleagues! This one is entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1139/cjfas-2017-0148&#34;&gt;Use of multielement stable isotope ratios to investigate ontogenetic movements of &lt;em&gt;Micropogonias furnieri&lt;/em&gt; in a tropical Brazilian estuary&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; and was lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Ana_Pizzochero&#34;&gt;Carolina Pizzochero&lt;/a&gt;. We used stable isotope ratios of C, N and S to track habitat use by whitemouth croakers (a commercially important fish from Southeastern Brazil) throughout their life. It&#39;s the lead author&#39;s first paper, so congrats Carolina! You can read the paper here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/214593&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/214593&#34;&gt;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/214593&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_372&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;2600&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/cjfas-2017-0148f5.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/cjfas-2017-0148f5.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;cjfas-2017-0148f5&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Diagram summarising the hypothesized whitemouth croaker, &lt;em&gt;Micropogonias furnieri&lt;/em&gt;, habitat shift in Guanabara Bay over the fish growth. Three regions are indicated: A, inner bay; B, entrance of the bay; C, continental shelf waters.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper about isotopic fractionation in Arctic seals</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-about-isotopic-fractionation-in-arctic-seals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 14:18:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-about-isotopic-fractionation-in-arctic-seals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7955&#34;&gt;Carbon, Nitrogen and Sulphur isotopic fractionation in captive juvenile hooded seal (&lt;em&gt;Cystophora cristata&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.7955&#34;&gt;): application for diet analysis&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; just came out in Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry. We took advantage of a rare opportunity to analyse tissues from Arctic seals raised on controlled diets to investigate diet-consumer isotopic fractionation in multiple tissues, and compare experimentally measured trophic enrichment factors to outputs from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/healyke/SIDER&#34;&gt;SIDER&lt;/a&gt;, a recently published model. Congrats to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MissMpinzone&#34;&gt;Marianna Pinzone&lt;/a&gt;, the lead author!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SCAR Biology Symposium, Leuven</title>
      <link>/post/scar-biology-symposium-leuven/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2017 14:39:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/scar-biology-symposium-leuven/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just spent the week in Leuven for the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://kuleuvencongres.be/scarbiology2017/&#34;&gt;12th Scientific Committee on Antarctic Research Biology Symposium&lt;/a&gt;. Between a talk, a poster, a session to chair, scheduled project meetings and countless great presentations and fortuitous discussions, it has been a busy, productive, and very enjoyable week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_381&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;2048&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/den5msmxyaefaqk.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/den5msmxyaefaqk.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;DEn5MsMXYAEFAQk&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; University of Liège&#39;s delegation at the SCAR Biology Symposium in Leuven[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>West Antarctic Peninsula workshop in Cambridge</title>
      <link>/post/west-antarctic-peninsula-workshop-in-cambridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 14:57:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/west-antarctic-peninsula-workshop-in-cambridge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On 15 &amp;amp; 16/05, I took part in the 1st Workshop of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.soos.aq/&#34;&gt;Southern Ocean Observing System&lt;/a&gt; (SOOS) &amp;ldquo;West Antarctic Peninsula Regional Working Group&amp;rdquo;, held at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bas.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;British Antarctic Survey&lt;/a&gt; in Cambridge (UK). It&#39;s been a pleasure to attend the many high-quality talks, to participate in the discussions, and to discover the mythic BAS offices!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_387&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;2048&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/c_4vslrxyaex0in.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/c_4vslrxyaex0in.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;C_4VsLrXYAEX0in&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If you&#39;re into that sort of stuff, here&#39;s a great opportunity to play &amp;ldquo;Find Waldo&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BASIS symposium 2017, Utrecht</title>
      <link>/post/basis-symposium-2017-utrecht/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2017 14:49:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/basis-symposium-2017-utrecht/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Gilles_Lepoint&#34;&gt;Gilles Lepoint&lt;/a&gt; and I are just back from lovely Utrecht (The Netherlands), where we attended the 2017 Symposium of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.basis-online.eu/en/&#34;&gt;Benelux Association of Stable Isotope Scientists&lt;/a&gt;. As always, it was a very convivial meeting, and a great opportunity to meet with peopled involved in IRMS instrumentation development. I gave a talk about our research on &lt;a href=&#34;https://orbi.uliege.be/handle/2268/210019&#34;&gt;impacts of changes in sea ice cover on Antarctic Benthic communities&lt;/a&gt;. Next year, Gilles and I will happily host the symposium in Liège!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_384&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;2048&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/c-ij7dxuaarbdo.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/c-ij7dxuaarbdo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;C&amp;ndash;IJ7dXUAARbDO&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Live from Utrecht[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper about cardinalfishes niche segregation in Malagasy coral reefs</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-about-cardinalfishes-niche-segregation-in-malagasy-coral-reefs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 14:24:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-about-cardinalfishes-niche-segregation-in-malagasy-coral-reefs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bruno Frédérich and I co-first authored a paper about resource segregation in relatively poorly known nocturnal fishes from coral reefs in Madagascar. It&#39;s open access, so go read it on Zoological Studies&amp;rsquo; website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://zoolstud.sinica.edu.tw/Journals/56/56-10.html&#34;&gt;Comparative Feeding Ecology of Cardinalfishes (Apogonidae) at Toliara Reef, Madagascar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out in Marine Environmental Research</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-out-in-marine-environmental-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 14:32:22 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-out-in-marine-environmental-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper about differences in niche width in populations of fin whales from the Atlantic and the Mediterranean, and the implications for conservation biology just came out in Marine Environmental Research. It&#39;s entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marenvres.2017.03.009&#34;&gt;Isotopic niches of fin whales from the Mediterranean Sea and the Celtic Sea (North Atlantic)&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, it was lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Krishna_Das&#34;&gt;Krishna Das&lt;/a&gt;, and I was in charge of the isotopic niche modelling. Read it here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/208463&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/208463&#34;&gt;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/208463&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out in Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry</title>
      <link>/post/new-paper-out-in-rapid-communications-in-mass-spectrometry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2017 16:42:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-paper-out-in-rapid-communications-in-mass-spectrometry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our latest paper, entitled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/wol1/doi/10.1002/rcm.7838/abstract&#34;&gt;Isotopic half-life and enrichment factor in two species of European freshwater fish larvae: an experimental approach&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, just came out in the last issue of Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry. For this paper, we set up a lab experiment to measure isotopic turnover and trophic fractionation of carbon and nitrogen in larvae two species of common freshwater fish from river Meuse, the chub (&lt;em&gt;Squalius cephalus&lt;/em&gt;) and the roach (&lt;em&gt;Rutilus rutilus&lt;/em&gt;). It&#39;s the lead author (Adrien Latli, from UNamur) &amp;lsquo;s first paper, so congratulations Adrien! You can read the paper here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/208223&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/208223&#34;&gt;http://hdl.handle.net/2268/208223&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VLIZ Marine Science Day 2017</title>
      <link>/post/vliz-marine-science-day-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 16:14:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/vliz-marine-science-day-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vliz.be/&#34;&gt;VLIZ (Flanders Marine Institute)&lt;/a&gt; organized the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vliz.be/vmsd/en/VMSD17&#34;&gt;2017 edition of its annual Marine Science Day&lt;/a&gt; on Friday 03/03 in Bruges. I was selected to give a talk in the afternoon. Slots were very short (5 minutes), which provided a challenging but interesting experience. Overall, the scientific quality was impressive, and the organisation was flawless (as always with VLIZ). A very enjoyable day and an excellent networking opportunity. Looking forward for the 2018 edition!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_266&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;394&amp;rdquo;]&lt;a href=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/120051.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/120051.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Photo: VLIZ (Reynaert, Stefanie)[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Article on the French National Museum of Natural History expedition blog</title>
      <link>/post/article-on-the-french-national-museum-of-natural-history-expedition-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 10:18:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/article-on-the-french-national-museum-of-natural-history-expedition-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jerome_Fournier&#34;&gt;Jérôme Fournier&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Marc_Eleaume&#34;&gt;Marc Eleaume&lt;/a&gt; are currently in Dumont-d&#39;Urville station for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://expeditions-antarctiques.mnhn.fr/fr/missions/revolta-2016-2017&#34;&gt;sixth REVOLTA campaign&lt;/a&gt;. Among many other things, they are collecting invertebrate samples to complement our data on &lt;a href=&#34;http://orbi.ulg.ac.be/handle/2268/195134&#34;&gt;recent changes of food web structure in Adélie Land&lt;/a&gt;. They asked me to write to a short post about this research for their &lt;a href=&#34;http://expeditions-antarctiques.mnhn.fr/fr&#34;&gt;expedition blog&lt;/a&gt;. You can &lt;a href=&#34;http://expeditions-antarctiques.mnhn.fr/fr/carnet-bord/carnet-bord-scientifiques/pourquoi-recolte-t-organismes-marins&#34;&gt;read it here&lt;/a&gt;  (French only, sorry).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_188&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;quot;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;quot;676&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://loicnmichel.files.wordpress.com/2016/10/ammotheaseastarsfull.jpg?w=676&#34; alt=&#34;ammotheaseastarsfull&#34;&gt; Some of the species that we study in Adélie Land: the pycnogonid &lt;em&gt;Decolopoda australis&lt;/em&gt; and the sea star &lt;em&gt;Odontaster validus&lt;/em&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Videos from the Kerguelen campaign</title>
      <link>/post/videos-from-the-kerguelen-campaign/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 14:25:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/videos-from-the-kerguelen-campaign/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.proteker.net/?lang=en&#34;&gt;PROTEKER&lt;/a&gt; campaign in Kerguelen Islands, as part of an outreach initiative, several videos were shot about the journey and the research program. One of them focuses specifically on my research (French only, sorry about that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[youtube &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eNVStleK0Yw&amp;amp;w=560&amp;amp;h=315&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eNVStleK0Yw&amp;amp;w=560&amp;amp;h=315&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see all the other videos &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLXPucz7oiNMFIttNjU7ov_Ed1FgvEMAzx&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately most are in French, but non-French speakers can still enjoy this one that focuses on the benthic ecosystems of the archipelago and whose soundtrack is only music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[youtube &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c0hCyblbxSM&amp;amp;w=560&amp;amp;h=315&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c0hCyblbxSM&amp;amp;w=560&amp;amp;h=315&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
